So in the last lecture we added our own middleware which is a logging middleware outputting something
Son dersimizde, bir eylem gnderirken bir eyler ktlayan bir gnle kaydetme Mitla
whenever we dispatch an action.
olan kendi ara katmann ekledik.
Now this is nice and it allows us to get some insights into our store but only if we dispatched an action,
Hayr, bu ho deil ve hikayemize baz bilgiler vermemize izin veriyor, ancak ancak
that would be more useful if we could always look into the store.
hikayeyi her zaman inceleyebilirlerse daha yararl olaca bir eylem gnderdik.
Now in the debugging section, we learned about the react dev tools and there, we can have a look at all the
imdi, hata ayklama blmnde, tepki alan DAPH aralarn rendik ve bileenlerin tm
components, the component tree and the state of each of that.
bileenlerini ve bunlarn her birinin durumunu inceleyebiliriz.
And for the provider for example, we get the store but there we only see the utility functions,
Ve rnein salayc iin maazay edindik, ancak yalnzca yardmc program ilevlerini gryoruz.
we don't really see what's inside the store.
Maazann iinde ne olduunu gerekten grmyoruz.
So this isn't that great, now
Bu yzden imdi bu harika deil.
there are ways to work around that, if
Bununla baa kmann yollar var.
we click on the counter component for example, we see the current value of the counter prop
Kar bileenini tklarz, rnein saya Propp'un imdiki deerini grrz.
but still, it's difficult if we have to navigate to a component which gets a certain slice of the state
Ancak, dilimin tam maazaya bakmak iin daha ho olacan grmek ve
just to see that slice, would be nicer to be able to look at the full store and even see the actions
hatta geriye sarlm olan eylemleri grmek iin belirli bir dilim alan bir
which were dispatched, maybe even rewind.
bileene gitmek zorundaysak, yine de zor.
Well for that there are special developer tools we can install, if you google for redux dev tools,
Bunun iin, Google'n okuma dev aralar iin google'da ykleyebileceiniz zel gelitirici aralar var.
you'll find two results,
ki sonu bulacaksnz.
the second one, the redux dev tools extension or to be precise, the third one the redux dev tools
kincisi okundu ex-staff dev aralar uzants veya kesin olmak iin redux dev aralar nichrome
in the chrome web store,
web maazas nc.
that's an interesting thing.
Bu ilgin bir ey.
You should install this extension to Chrome,
Bu uzanty Chrome'a yklemeniz gerekir.
it will give you a nice plugin you can use to look into your store.
Size gzel bir fi verecek ve maazanza bakmak iin kullanabilirsiniz.
Now you can read more instructions on that second result,
imdi ikinci sonu hakknda daha fazla talimat okuyabilirsiniz.
the redux dev tools extension github repository, here you'll find more instructions about how to install and
tools uzants deposu burada, ykleme ve kurulum hakknda daha fazla talimat bulacak ve sper basit olacak,
set it up, in the end it's super simple, you just need to download that extension and install it and you're
sadece o uzanty indirmeniz ve yklemeniz gerekecek ve olduka fazla iiniz bitti.
pretty much done.
Redux dev
One more step is required though
Geri bir adm daha gerekiyor.
but I will of course also walk you through the required steps.
Ancak elbette gerekli admlarla da sizi ynlendirecektir.
Now important, don't have a look at the first result here,
nemli olan burada ilk sonuca bakmayn.
these are also dev tools which you can implement programmatically into your app,
Bunlar, programnzda uygulamanza uygulayabileceiniz tm dev aralardr.
we want to have that browser extension though.
Bu tarayc uzantsna sahip olmak istiyoruz.
So there, we see the steps we need to apply,
Dolaysyla, uygulamak zorunda olduumuz admlar gryoruz.
now assume you already installed the dev tools, if you then open them via your developer tools, there should
daha nce yklediyseniz, daha sonra aarsanz gelitirici aralarnz redktr seenei olmaldr.
be a redux option now,
imdi def aralarn
might have to switch back to the console first.
nce konsola geri dnmek zorunda kalabilir.
You should see the redux dev tools open up here on the right,
Burada redoks gelitirme aralarnn sada olduunu grmelisiniz.
now it's saying no store found because we haven't followed the second step where we have to basically
imdi maazann bulunmadn sylyor nk ikinci admdan gemedik ve bu uzanty
inform this extension that there is a store in our web app and for that, we simply need to set up a special
temel olarak web uygulamamzda bir maaza olduunu ve bunun iin yalnzca burada zel bir deiken
variable here or pass a special enhancer we should say to our create store method. Since we're using a
ayarlamamz veya zel gelitirilmi ya da katman yazlmn kullandmz iin maaza oluturma yntemimize sylemeliyiz,
middleware we have to use the advance store set up
nceden kurulmu maazay kullanmamz gerekiyor.
but it's still pretty simple. Let's copy that strangely named variable here on the window object,
Fakat hala olduka basit, bu garip adlandrlm deikeni burada pencere nesnesinde kopyalalm.
the redux dev tools extension compose thing here, this essentially is a variable which is injected by
Redux def aralar uzants burada bir ey oluturuyor, esas olarak Chrome uzants tarafndan
the Chrome extension into our javascript at runtime so it will be available. Back in our code in the
alma zamanmzda javascript'imize eklenmi bir deiken var, bu nedenle sonraki kodumuzda takip edilecek ekilde
index.js file where
tekrar kullanlabilir.
we create our store,
Bir dkkan yaratyoruz.
I will first of all as instructed here create a custom constant before we do anything on the store, I'll
Her eyden nce talimatnamede belirtildii gibi maazada herhangi bir ey yapmadan nce zel bir sablon yaratacam.
name it composeEnhancers. This will then be our special variable or in case that can't be found,
Btn adlar ve bunu oluturan ve oluturan cevaplar, daha sonra zel deiken olacak ya da bulunamyorsa salanan
we'll fall back to a default compose function provided by redux,
bir varsaylan hazrlama ilevine geri dnecektir. redux tarafndan
you can import it from the redux package.
Redoks paketinden ie aktarabilirsiniz.
Now compose is a little bit similar to combineReducers, combineReducers allows us to combine well
imdi kompoze etmek kombine redktrlere biraz benzemektedir, indirgeyiciler kombine etmemize olanak tanyan iyi
reducers, compose allows us to combine enhancers, applyMiddleware is only for middlewares if we have
redktrler birletirmemizi salyor, birletirmemizi salyor ve Hans'n uygulad orta katman sadece orta iin, oysa
other enhancers like the store dev tools, we need to use compose to compose a set of enhancers with both
operatr gelitiricileri def aralarn saklamak istiyorlarsa, kompozisyonu oluturmak iin kompozisyon kullanmamz gerekiyor. Hem def aralar zellikleri
the dev tools features and our middleware.
hem de katman yazlmyla cevaplar kmesi.
So we also add compose here, separate it with this or sign to take this dynamically injected variable if available
Bu yzden de bizden ayr bir besteci ekliyoruz veya metin atamak dinamik olarak bu ar deikene enlemesine pskrtyor.
but if not, to still have to fall back to the native redux solution which of course doesn't give us dev
Fakat tabii ki bizi destekleyecek sar olmayan doal redoks zmne geri
tools support then.
dnmek zorunda kalmazsak.
So now composeEnhancers essentially just holds a function,
imdi kapos arttrclar aslnda sadece bir ilevi tutar.
if we go back to the documentation,
Belgelere dnyoruz.
we see that now we should create our store and use this new composeEnhancers function which uses either
imdi, maazamz oluturmal ve def aralar ilevini kullanan ya da
the dev tools function or the natively built-in one to then pass applyMiddleware to it.
yerleik olan kullanarak katman uygulamasn geirmeyi salayan yeni kompozisyon arttrclar ilevini kullanmalyz.
So we'll do that,
O zaman bunu yapacaz.
I will wrap applyMiddleware in create store with composeEnhancers,
Kompozit arttrclarla create store'da middleware uygulayacam.
so with this constant name here composeEnhancers, wrap applyMiddleware with it so pass applyMiddleware
Yani burada bu sabit ismi ile gelitiricileri wrap uygulamal katman yazlmn oluturun, dolaysyla katman yazlmn bunun bir
as a function to that,
fonksiyonu olarak uygulayn.
you don't need to pass anything about the dev tools because it will be passed in automatically, if
ihtiyacnz yoktur nk verilerden seilen veriler kullanlabilir olduunda otomatik olarak aktarlr.
that is chosen, so if that is available.
Def aralaryla ilgili hibir eyi aktarmaya
So we got a set up where we should be able to connect our browser extension to the store running in
Bu nedenle, tarayc eklentimizi Javascript kodumuzda alan maazaya balayabilmemiz iin
our Javascript code.
bir ayarmz var.
Let's have a look, let's go back to the react application and there, you should already see that the
Bir gz atalm yeniden eylem uygulamasna geri dnelim ve oradaki X
redux view here is filled with life.
okumasnn hayatla dolu olduunu zaten greceksiniz.
Here you see all actions which were emitted, like the init action which happens first,
Burada ilk nce gerekleen init eylemi gibi yaylan tm eylemleri gryorsunuz.
can shrink this to get a different view on this
Bununla farkl bir gr edinmek iin kar koymak.
and there you see for each action, what type this was or which payload it actually carried,
Ve her eylem iin bunun ne tip olduunu veya hangi ykn tandn gryorsunuz.
also anything besides type, what the state is at this point of time, how it changed the state
Ayn zamanda, devlet bu noktada devletin nasl bir deiim geirdiini yazn.
and you can always look into the state therefore with this state button at a given point of time.
Belli bir zamanda bu durum dmesiyle daima duruma bakabilirsiniz.
Now if I dispatch a new action by for example subtracting 15, you'll see it gets added here
rnein imdi 15 kararak yeni bir eylem gnderirsem, burada eklendiini greceksin.
and if you click on it, we see what the state is after this action, this state here,
Ve ona tklarsanz, devletin ne yaptna bakarz, burada bu devlet hareketi yapar.
you also see the old state if you click on the action, on the init action,
Birim eylemindeki eylemi tklarsanz, eski durumu da grrsnz.
so you see the state at different points of times. You'll see how the subtract action changed the state,
Yani devleti farkl zamanlarda grdnzde, karma eyleminin tezgahn dna 15
it deducted 15 off the counter and you'll see what the action carried,
algladnn durumunu nasl deitireceini greceksiniz ve gerekleen eylemi greceksiniz.
that's pretty useful.
Olduka kullanl.
Now we can add more and more and we can always see how we adjusted our state and what our current state
imdi, giderek daha ok ey ekleyebiliriz ve durumumuzu nasl ayarladmz ve halihazrdaki durumumuzun ve
is and what our state was in the past.
devletin gemiindeki durumunun ne olduunu grebiliriz.
So redux dev tools are extremely useful and definitely dive into the documentation I pointed you to
Bu yzden Rydex dev aralar son derece kullanldr ve size daha fazla bilgi edinmek
to learn more about them.
iin iaret ettiim dokmantasyonlara dalyorlar.
Now one important feature I want to show you is the time traveling, with the redux dev tools,
imdi sana gstermek istediim nemli bir zellik redux dev aralar ile seyahat zaman.
you can travel through time.
Zaman iinde dolaabilirsiniz.
So for example, of course the application we see here reflects the state after all these actions
rnein elbette burada grdmz uygulama tm bu eylemlerin ardndan devleti yanstyor.
but if we wanted to rewind and say yes let's go back to that subtracting here, you can click on subtract and
sarmak ve eer burada karsan kalm diyelim ki, karma ve ardndan rek zerine tklayabilirsiniz.
then on jump
Fakat eer geri
and now you see you are back to that point of time where you just subtracted 15.
Ve imdi grdn gibi, sadece 50 karldn zamann l noktasna geri dnyorsun.
Now the old states are not lost,
Artk eski devletler kaybolmad.
you can always go back to there by clicking jump on that again
Yeniden tklayarak blme her zaman gidebilirsiniz.
but you can also go back and for example skip this to update your state as if you haven't ever dispatched
Ancak yine geri dnebilir ve imdiye kadar hi bir hareket olarak gnderilmemi gibi durumunuzu gncellemek iin
this action
bunu atlayabilirsiniz.
and of course, this can also be reverted.
Ve tabii ki bu da yeniden ilenebilir.
So this is a extremely nice feature which gives you a lot of debugging possibilities and especially
sayda hata ayklama olana ve zellikle de daha karmak uygulamalar sunan son derece gzel bir zelliktir.
more complex apps,
Dolaysyla, size ok
this is great to make sure that only actions are dispatched you expected to be dispatched and to
Bu gnderilmesini beklediiniz sadece eylemlerin gnderildiinden ve devletin u an
find out why the state is currently in
iinde bulunduunu bulmak iin harika.
well the state it is in.
inde bulunduu durum.